









<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
            <copyright>© The Wrys</copyright>
        
        <description>News · The Wry Family</description>
        
            <language>en</language>
        
        
        <link>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/</link>
        
        
            <title>News · The Wry Family</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="another-module-conquered">Another Module Conquered</h1>
<p>It’s hard to believe CC3D has seen its 10th week done. 8 Modules and counting, only 26 to go! It seems the year is going by way too quickly!! Check out our calendar <a href="https://cc3d.org/calendario/">here</a>!</p>
<p>This past week we went through an introduction to Ancient Greek. This is the language the New Testament was written in and is very helpful to have a grasp for Bible study. It just so happens that the invited teacher was not able to attend and it was a daunting task for John to take on. Yet God gave peace to proceed and we decided to move forward with the module. God was good and we feel it was a very productive week. A couple of students expressed how fun it was. How amazing for us to watch the students reciting and writing the Greek alphabet and memorizing [John 3:16](<a href="https://biblia.com/bible/nasb95/John">https://biblia.com/bible/nasb95/John</a> 3.16) in Greek!</p>
<p><img src="https://cloud.cc3d.org/index.php/s/SffJdLKDfi5KD9T/preview" alt="img">Celebrating the finish of Introduction to Greek</p>
<h2 id="josh-nanawe-and--">Josh, Nanawe and ??? …</h2>
<p><img src="https://cloud.cc3d.org/index.php/s/ZrfCpfs4jFKdBaZ/preview" alt="img">??Josh, Nanawe and</p>
<p>Here’s a picture we wanted to share of Joshua playing hugging our loaner dog Nanawe. Uzai, one of the invited teachers has loaned him to us since he has to place to keep him in the meantime.</p>
<p>The other puppy (right) is new. It is a female and meant to be a buddy for Nanawe since he howls and whines when we go out. Hopefully they will be good together but how about helping us out with ideas for names? We’d love to hear any ideas from you!</p>
<h2 id="johns-b-day">John’s B-day</h2>
<p><img src="https://cloud.cc3d.org/index.php/s/3eiQiKSqb55aajo/preview" alt="img">Susy, John, Joshua and Jorge</p>
<p>John just celebrated his 48th. The neighbors, Susy and Jorge came over to congratulate him.</p>
<p>The day started with eggs and bacon and coffee (John’s favorite). After spending the day teaching at CC3D, Nelly took John to get a nice leather bag for his iPad (50% off at the store because it’s John’s birthday). Then when John and Nelly arrived home, the CC3D students gave a surprise party to him. They had decorated the house and Rachel had baked all sorts of goodies. What a day!</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/another-module/</guid>
                    <link>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/another-module/</link>
                
                
                
                    <title>2022 Second Quarter</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="2022-quarterly-update">2022 Quarterly Update</h1>
<p>We praise God for his goodness! He is faithful, loving and ever patient as He interacts with us. I would like to sum up some of the main events in our life this year as a testimony and reminder of that.</p>
<p>We arrived back in Bolivia in August 2021 with the purpose of setting up a gap year training center. By January we were well on our way towards having a place picked out and beginning to prepare it as a place</p>
<p>For learning. We were also involved with starting a local gathering of believers. These were instrumental in getting the place ready as well.</p>
<p>Classes began on the first day of February with 5 students. One week later we had 7 and ended up with 8.</p>
<p>From February to early May (13 weeks) we studied through <strong>11 modules</strong>.</p>
<ol>
<li>The Stranger on the Road to Emmaus</li>
<li>Knowing God (From Eden to Calvary)</li>
<li>Romans 1-8</li>
<li>Biblical Discipleship</li>
<li>Old Testament Panorama</li>
<li>Galatians</li>
<li>Colossians</li>
<li>Introduction to Greek</li>
<li>Life of Christ Panorama</li>
<li>Bible Study Methods</li>
<li>Romans 9-16 (away)</li>
</ol>
<p>Several (7) teachers were involved helping with the teaching that came from different parts of Bolivia. These were trained by DM2 attendees through workshops done between about 2008-2019. Three teachers were from a local church in Cochabamba.</p>
<p>All in all (though not without challenges) we have seen and tasted the program to be highly effective in training young people for one year that prepares them for the rest of their lives. Roughly about <strong>330 hours</strong> of intense Bible teaching was done this year.</p>
<p>Due to the fact that we closed the school halfway through this year, most of the students plan to return next year to complete their studies.</p>
<p>As you all know by now, our son went to be with the Lord. We’ve been advised to take time off the field to heal. We will plan to be in the US and Canada until around the end of the year and return in time for next year’s classes to begin in February.</p>
<p>I will leave you with some <strong>testimonies</strong> from students regarding CC3D (3D training center). I ran them through Google translate without editing.
<img src="https://usercontent.one/wp/thewrys.redbiblica.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/B612_20220322_134547_619.jpg" alt="img"></p>
<p>“<em>My name is Belen Soza, I am 19 years old, it all started with an ambition to know and be able to learn, I felt the need that there was something more to learn, something more beautiful to know, so God gave me the opportunity to study Bible one year, where the study of the bible was done in a different way, because each verse was studied in detail, the idea of being able to go to a place where the bible is studied intensively fascinated me, since that was what I wanted so much , God opened the doors in a supernatural way and everything went according to his will.</em></p>
<p><em>The months that God allowed me to be in the CC3D have been a great blessing in my life, since I have learned a lot and have been able to grow in the knowledge of God, but I still have a long way to go, a desire that I have in me is to be pleasant to my lord, in everything I do and every day learn more of his word and in the months that I was there I have been able to fulfill part of that wish. Being in the CC3D I have been able to learn a lot from the Bible, since we have studied the word of God in the way in which it has been revealed and how God has wanted to communicate towards the human being, I have been able to appreciate the importance that the cultural, historical, social context at the time of studying the scriptures, all of this has been very helpful to now see Christian life from another perspective and to be able to live it in a way that God wants me to live it, not as a false religion, but as a true relationship of a Father towards his children.</em></p>
<p><em>Being able to know God in the essence and simplicity with which it is shown through the scriptures, makes it possible for us to understand his love for humanity, revealed through JESUS CHRIST, since he left nothing hidden, but on the contrary, it is revealed clear way for all humanity and thus live the way He wants us to live through FAITH knowing our identity in CHRIST, counting on the blessings we already have for the work of CHRIST, all this makes our look above of what is on this earth and points only to Christ, what this produces in us is the work of God and takes away the focus on our strengths or our abilities, it leads us to realize that our sufficiency comes from CHRIST, that in Him we are already complete and our focus is no longer on what we can do, but on what He has already done on the Cross and that is what the Christian life of living by faith is all about, faith in what Christ has already done, this makes me love to a living and true God who he has already done everything for me, there is no need to make an effort to please him, since being in Christ I am pleasing to the father, the word of God produces its transcendental effect in our lives, it produces a genuine change, it produces a passion for preaching the gospel, teaching and disciple others, tell them our condition outside of God and give them the solution that is through Faith in the Gospel, so that they know a just God, a God of Grace and this truth spreads transforming religious lives or lives without God , in fruitful, sincere lives, full of faith living in the GRACE that we were called to live</em>.”</p>
<p>—-</p>
<p><img src="https://usercontent.one/wp/thewrys.redbiblica.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1081E19C-9D37-443B-BBFC-5B9203DC1EB8.jpeg" alt="img"></p>
<p><em>“My name is Silvia Herboso Meneses, I live in Cochabamba-Bolivia, an older single woman, a believer in Christ Jesus for 32 years. This year God blessed me by studying at the CC3D Study Center, it was a great blessing to study the blessed word of God verse by verse, to deepen the super abundant richness of God’s Grace!!!</em></p>
<p><em>Many truths of his Word remained in my mind and heart, among them I will cite the understanding that “I was a sinner without hope” but, Jesus in his infinite LOVE and GRACE paid the price of my REDEMPTION!!! He gave me hope by including myself in his family, the family of God.</em></p>
<p><em>I understood that: “EVERYTHING is by GRACE.” We are justified through FAITH in Christ Jesus. ([Romans 3:21-31](<a href="https://biblia.com/bible/nasb95/Rom">https://biblia.com/bible/nasb95/Rom</a> 3.21-31))</em></p>
<p><em>The book of Romans is a great blessing for my life, I understood many things about our sinfulness, and God’s PERFECT JUSTICE, I would lack many sheets to write, all the profound truths I learned in CC3D, “Romans, Galatians, Philemon, Colossians, etc. By meditating and savoring the Richness of the WORD of GOD!</em></p>
<p><em>Therefore, I do not hesitate to recommend and encourage anyone to be part of DM2 and CC3D studies, because for me it was BLESSING and SPIRITUAL growth.”</em></p>
<p><em>—-</em></p>
<p>We <strong>thank God</strong> for the privilege it has been to be a small part of what He did in the lives of these people.</p>
<p>We ask your continued prayers as we continue to heal and look ahead to the future.</p>
<p>God’s grace and peace be with you.</p>
<p>John</p>
<p><img src="https://usercontent.one/wp/thewrys.redbiblica.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/4487AE08-8951-4BA8-A886-32C1E11550A5.jpeg" alt="img"></p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/2022-quarter3/</guid>
                    <link>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/2022-quarter3/</link>
                
                
                
                    <title>2022 Third Quarter</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="coch-arrival">Coch Arrival</h1>
<p>Posted on <a href="https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/coch-arrival/">August 22, 2021</a> by <a href="https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/author/johnwry/">John Wry</a></p>
<p>Here are some pictures we wanted to share with you of our first few days here in Cochabamba.</p>
<ul>
<li><img src="https://cloud.cc3d.org/index.php/apps/cms_pico/pico/wry-web//assets/20210820_193759-700x525.png" alt="img">Cochabamba lights</li>
<li><img src="https://cloud.cc3d.org/index.php/apps/cms_pico/pico/wry-web/assets/20210821_170338-525x700.png" alt="img">Joshua’s new friend Nacho</li>
<li><img src="https://cloud.cc3d.org/index.php/apps/cms_pico/pico/wry-web/assets/20210820_112306-525x700.png" alt="img">First means of Transportation</li>
</ul>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/coch-arrival/</guid>
                    <link>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/coch-arrival/</link>
                
                
                
                    <title>Cochabamba Arrival</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="rachels-wrap">Rachel’s Wrap</h1>
<p>Posted on <a href="https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/rachels-wrap/">April 24, 2019</a> by <a href="https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/author/johnwry/">John Wry</a></p>
<p><img src="https://cloud.cc3d.org/index.php/apps/cms_pico/pico/wry-web/assets/IMG_0292-1-768x1024.png" alt="img"></p>
<p>Rachel is our social butterfly. She loves people. She loves laughing and social events and sports. She does not love school and particularly homeschool where she is the only student.</p>
<p>So you can imagine she is looking forward to next semester, beginning 9th grade at Christian Life Academy a school John’s grandpa Earl started in Franklin, PA back in the 80’s. The standards are fairly high so she is nervous about being on level. Please pray for her as she diligently prepares during the next several months and that she would be ready for the challenge ahead.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/rachels-wrap/</guid>
                    <link>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/rachels-wrap/</link>
                
                
                
                    <title>Rachel’s Wrap</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="headed-home-from-a-great-first-experience-in-zambia">Headed home from a great first experience in Zambia!</h1>
<p>Posted on <a href="https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/headed-home-from-a-great-first-experience-in-zambia/">November 3, 2019</a> by <a href="https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/author/johnwry/">John Wry</a></p>
<p>
<span class="paige-image">
<img  alt="Landscape"   class="object-fit-cover rounded-4"  crossorigin="anonymous"  fetchpriority="high"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="/img/zambia.png"   style="height: 30rem; width: 90%"   >
</span>
</p>
<p>As I sit here in Lusaka, Zambia, and wait for my plane to go home tomorrow, I wanted to make sure I updated you with a few comments and a video.
What a great experience this has been! People are Zambia are so friendly and passionate. They EXPRESS their feelings (good and bad). They have no problem telling you what they are thinking.
The workshop was held at a church in Kasama, Zambia some 11 hours from Lusaka by car.</p>
<p>We put <a href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2sj3vLBbd8Y">this short video</a> together for you. We hope you like it! (Please subscribe so you get notified when we post new videos!). Leave your comments and questions below!</p>
<p>God’s abundant blessings upon you,</p>
<p>John</p>
<p>Here are some testimonies from the workshop. Please note, we’ve copied them exactly as they were written.</p>
<p>Testimonies Bible Study Methods</p>
<p>Zambia, 2019</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In this workshop, I have learnt the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>God paid the full price for my salvation</li>
<li>How to study the Word of God</li>
<li>How to observe, interpret and apply the Word of God in my life.</li>
<li>I have come to understand Psalms 23 in a more profound way</li>
<li>How to let the Scripture speak to me and not to add to the Scripture my perceived ideas.</li>
<li>yourAnd many more*</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><cite>Humphrey Mwbanga</cite></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I thank God for this workshop which has helped me know and understand how to prepare Bible study in the simplest way. Before, I never know that observation, interpretation and application are essential in preparing Bible study.</p>
<ul>
<li><cite>Bridget M Nkhonjera</cite></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This workshop has helped me how to conduct a Bible study. How to read the Bible and understand Bible passages and it also to avoid taking my experience and my culture in the Bible.</p>
<ul>
<li><cite>Jonathan Mwango</cite></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is an eyes opened for me in the Bible study It has made me grow on the Bible study preparation lesson It has inspired in me in Bible study.
<cite>Sibanse Lovemore B</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Isaiah N Kabuia</p>
<p><em>In this workshop I have learned a lot of things. I wasn’t know how to do Bible working and researching, but through this workshop my mind is now open. I can do the whole so objectively. There iss my prayer that may the all mighty God continue blessing you and give you more knowledge.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Daniel S Chisanga</p>
<p><em>In this workshop we have very much glad for everything we have learnt and we are pray it will take us a long way in our churches when we are going back.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Webster Mbulo</p>
<p><em>There was a time, pastor Chishimba, invited me for this workshop and was even telling me how the importance of DM2 was. And upon attending it I was interesting in it, now I don’t want to miss future workshops.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Joseph K Sikazkie</p>
<p><em>God used this workshop to help me how to clearly observe, interpret and apply the Word of God. This has prepared me how to understand God’s word properly and wonderfully. This has helped not to rush in preparation of Bible study and give a misleading words.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sishwati R. Mubita</p>
<p><em>God has really helped me know the right way to follow when teaching Bible study as before I was teaching it all wrongly.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Francis Sitali</p>
<p><em>I was ignorant how to prepare a message. But through DM2 teachings I have learned how to prepare for Bible study or Sunday service. This is great to me.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Keran C Kasonde</p>
<p><em>Through this workshop I have been enabled to take time to read texts, observe by taking down the key words. Previously I left our meaningful things because little did I pay attention the details.</em></p>
</blockquote>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/zambia-trip/</guid>
                    <link>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/zambia-trip/</link>
                
                
                
                    <title>Trip to Zambia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-wrys-family-updates">The Wry’s Family Updates</h1>
<h2 id="week-1">Week 1</h2>
<h5 id="--january-1st-2023-arrival-to-cochabamba">- January 1st, 2023 arrival to Cochabamba</h5>
<h5 id="--cell-phone-updates">- Cell phone updates</h5>
<h2 id="january-1st-2023-arrival">January 1st, 2023 Arrival</h2>
<p>After a few stops, we made it to Cochabamba along with all of our luggage! We were welcomed upon arriving at the house by Sonia and Señorita. Nelly’s brother Esteban and mother to follow shortly after.
Upon seeing all the things from the center in the living room it became quickly apparent there was a lot of work to be done before classes could begin one month later.</p>
<h2 id="cell-phone-updates-and-such">Cell Phone Updates and such</h2>
<p>It’s interesting to come back to Bolivia after being in North America for a little bit because you notice peculiar things that once you live in Bolivia for a while, become pretty day to day stuff.
Every time we come back in we have to reconnect our cell phones to a Bolivian cellphone carrier.
I had a phone I brought back with me from the US. It was not new and when I put in the new Bolivian SIM card it only worked for the first two minutes then showed no signal.
My first thought was I will have to buy a new one. The suggestion was given however that I take it to a cell phone repair place and have them look it over. So, even though I doubted it would work we all went into town to at least give this option a try, hopefully saving money from buying a new phone.
The first shop we stopped at asked me, “did you drop it?”. What a question. That’s like asking does a dog bark? Who hasn’t dropped their phone…? I paused a second before answering…ummm…(maybe it was a trick question?)…”yes” I replied realizing he was serious. “Oh…that’s bad, I’m going to need at least three days to repair it” was his reply. “How much?” I asked, his prompt reply, “350 Bolivianos”. So I went back out of the shop where Nelly and Joshua were waiting to discuss the option. It seemed way too much to pay to have a phone tampered with instead of just buying a new one. So, we decided to try out a second opinion. We headed to the next cell phone repair shop about a block away. “Oh”, was this young man’s return, “that’s no problem, give me an hour”. “How much” I enquired, “150 Bolivianos”. My reply, “can you do it for 100?”. He continued looking at the phone and replied, “let me see”.
In the meantime we sat and waited. It’s usually not the best idea to leave your phone, that is, unless you don’t care about what they do to it.
After an hour, a few screenshots and a bit of typing, he was done. “that will be 150 Bolivianos” he summoned, the looked up at me, “the hacker charged me 120, I only get 30”, he explained. Sure enough the phone was fixed, so off we went without asking questions.
We had intended to go look for cars after that but my stomach was bothering me. Nelly pointed around the corner, “over there” she said, pointing towards a friend chicken restaurant.
We went inside and not seeing a bathroom sign, went to the front counter and asked if we could use their bathroom. “It’s only for clients” was the ladies sturn reply. So we proceeded to buy a juice to share while I did my business. I went in back and asked for the bathroom. They pointed into a hallway so I (rather promptly) made my way there only to find it only contained a shower stall. By this time my stomach was really telling me it was time…or else…so I went back to ask where the bathroom was. Again they pointed toward the hallway but this time I could see they signaled to the other side of the hall where the door was almost impossible to spot as it was painted over just like the walls.
I made a dash for the door, pried it open and proceeded to…well…you get the picture. Only, there was no toilet paper! Oh no, run back out, ask the “so very helpful attendant” for toilet paper only to be ignored, as if to say, “juice-buying clients are not entitled to toilet paper”. Thankfully, a young man, obviously seeing my desperation, reached in a bag and pulled out a handful of napkins. It turns out there were exactly 5. I was sure grateful for those napkins, even though they were not quite enough…oh well.
Note to self: next time we return to Bolivia after being away a while, I shall take a bunch of TP with me in my back pocket and remember the location of this wonderful restaurant we are now “clients” of.
Anyway, these are the funny things you don’t really notice after living in it for a while.</p>
<h2 id="center-and-student-residence-secured">Center and student residence Secured</h2>
<p>We are thankful that a place to have the center, and large enough to also serve as the student residence has been secured. It’s right next door to one of the church elder’s house!
We still continue to search for a place nearby to live.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/2023/week01/</guid>
                    <link>https://thewrys.redbiblica.org/news/2023/week01/</link>
                
                
                
                    <title>Week 1</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
